Hey guys, Shandid welcome back to the
channel and today in spring
microservices we are going to do
centralized configuration and I can say
that in most of the companies which are
dealing with the spring boot they are
following the centralized configuration
approach only for managing the
configurations.
But let's see the problem first and with
that you will get to know better
understanding that why why everyone is
following the centralized configuration
approach. Okay, the first problem is
rebuild and redeploying. Assume that
this is your application order
application and this is the
application.properties where you are
maintaining your configuration. Now say
that you have to update this
configuration.
What you have to do? You have to edit
the application.properties file. Then
after that you have to rebuild your jar
and then redeploy the surface.
Okay. So just one configuration update
you have to rebuild and redeploy and
with that itself you can know that it's
a big pain. Okay.
Now the problem too is that inconsistent
config ac across services many time what
happen is there have similar
configuration across multiple
microservices like this. Let's say uh I
have a very big order microservices
which I have further divided into two
smaller microservices. One is pre-order
and another is post order application.
So both are different microservices
but both helps in
fulfilling the order itself pre-order
and post order. So definitely that the
DB which they are pointing to be the
same DB. Okay. And this is just a one
configuration. There can be many
configuration which are common across
multiple microservices. So this is just
one example. So whenever you are making
any update or adding a new property
file, you have to make sure that it is
consistent across all the microservices.
Okay. So that is another challenge.
Okay. Now let's say that you change the
DB. You have made the change to order DB
to something else and you made only
changes in the pre-order. you forgot to
make change into the post order
application then it's uh become
inconsistent configuration across
different applications.
The third problem is no runtime update.
This is very important. Now let's say
that your application is already running
in live and
you need to change certain
configuration. Okay. Then
how your application which is running in
live can see those configuration
changes. Is it possible? Currently no.
Because application.property
file is loaded only once at a startup.
When your application is getting you are
starting your application let's say
order application only that time it read
application.property
file. Okay. After that if you make any
changes into this one there is no way
that runtime itself while this
application is running it observe the
changes okay this has been updated there
is no way okay so you have to stop it
okay you have to rebuild it and then you
have to deploy it again currently this
is the way okay if you have
application.properties properties at
with the particular microser.
What is the problem for time consuming
roll back? I told you that if any
configuration change you make you have
to let's say raise the PR get it merged
then you have to build the service again
and then you have to redeploy everything
has to be done and if any issue comes
you have to follow the complete process
again which is a time-conuming process
okay so that's what I have mentioned it
here you have to manually add it you
have to rebuild You have to redeploy. If
multiple service are impacted, you need
to fix all. Like in this example, let's
say if DB URL has you have done
misconfiguration, then you have to do
the same process for this pre-order
application. You have to do the same
process for post- orderer application.
Okay. So the roll back is time
consuming.
So what's the solution for that?
Solution for is centralized
configuration with spring cloud config.
Very important. you will find mostly
companies are using this.
Okay. So here
the first you can say that this is the
our layer one in the first layer which
is we have our config files. So we
create a g repository
just to store the config files. Okay.
This is where we put our dotproperties
files. Okay.
Even though you have multiple
microservices for all the microservices
we we have to put the configuration
files property files here in this git
repository.
Okay. So this is our first thing we will
see we will go in depth of each of layer
uh separately.
So this is the first thing. Now the
second thing is another micros service
config server. So its task is to fetch
the config from the g. So here so this
config server fetches the
application.properties
from this g repository where we have
only the property files. Okay. And in
the layer three you can say that we have
our microservices individual
microservices
it connect with the config server. Okay.
So you can say that order is connecting
with config server and saying that hey
can you help me fetch the properties for
this order application. It goes to the
config
files get repository where the
properties files are there. It fetches
the property from there and provided to
the order service.
Okay.
So now let's go one by one at each
service.
Let's say step one setting up the config
file repository. Okay. So within this
repository we know that we have to keep
all the property file for all the
microservices. Okay. So I created a
simple git repository nothing like a
maven project or nothing simple git
repository which has plain files
application.propy files yes you can
group it under a particular folder also
so like I have created one folder global
there I have put all these properties
application property application hyphen
div.tproperty
application hyphen prod and application
hyphen qa.propy property. So these are
different profiles and before I proceed
further if you have any doubt with the
profile we have already covered in depth
into the spring boot series like so we
have seen like what is Dave QA pro
profiles okay so kindly check it out
like if you have any doubt with this
like okay what does uh application
hyphen dev do.propy property means and
uh respectively other files also. Okay.
So
these are global files. Okay. I name
into the folder global and I have put
application.properties and it's
different profile like Dave pro QA.
Similarly I have created one folder
order service. Within that I have put
all the application all the property
files for the order service. Now here if
you see that if I have your let's say
this is your service order service and
within that application doproperty file
you give the application name so name is
you have given let's say order service
so the same name you have to use it here
okay so for a particular specific
application
you have to use application name
application name let's say order hyphen
service.properties properties order -
service - Dave.properties. So different
profiles hyphen Dave hyphen prod QA. So
these are the different profiles for the
order services. Okay. Similarly, if you
have different other microservices like
invoice, you can create different folder
invoice service and whatever the name
you have used in the invoice
application. We will see that in when we
will write the whole code, we will see
that the same name you have to use it.
Let's say invoice - service.properties
invoice- service Dave.properties
likewise. Okay. Now very important is
the precedence. Okay.
These global why I have why I have
specifically term the name global. Why?
Because application.properties
and these are all you can say that
applies to all the microservices.
For example, let's say you have global
and you have application do.properties
Dave QA prod likewise. Similarly, you
have order
it's order service.property order
service hyphen Dave hyphen QA - likewise
similarly for invoice. Similarly, you
have payment service. Okay. So, let's
say you have different microservices.
So this global act as a fall back
okay fall back for which configuration.
Now let's say that you are specifically
looking for order and let's say this
Dave hey you are looking for
configuration within this order service
and to the Dave configuration. So if
that configuration is missing here then
it will follow certain sequence to okay
what is the next fall back can I fall
back to this global okay if yes and if
configuration found then it will use
that so that's where I mean that very
important
to understand the precedence so I will
come to this points later the first I
will want to explain you the precedence
which This is very important and
understand this with this example first.
So we will see this example first then
we will see this generic one and then we
will read this uh this one then it will
become super clear.
Now let's say you are this is your
application order service. This is your
application and you are looking for
config profile
div. Okay. So currently let's say you
are working with the profile div. So
what is the precedence? So first it will
look for order - service -
Dave.properties.
Okay. So this is the first precedence.
Okay. Now let's say that your
configuration is missing in this one.
Then it will fall back to
I told you that these are the global
this act as a fallback. Now if you're
looking for this configuration within
this Dave and the configuration is
missing here it fall back to the global
one but global one which one there are
so many so you are looking for hyphen
Dave right so it will first fall back to
this hyphen Dave
okay so application Dave.property
property. So this is a global one but
it's a specific profile whatever you are
looking for. Now let's say that again
you the configuration is missing here.
Okay. So now what it will do? Let's go
back here. Now the configuration is
missing also here in this div. So should
I fall back to this one or should I fall
back to order service.properties.
Okay. So
see application.properties properties is
fallback for all profile Dave pro qa.
Okay. Similarly, order - service
properties is fallback for all div QA.
Okay. So, first what internally does
that it tried to look into the Dave
itself application dot application
Dave.properties
which is a global one but a specific
profile. Now if it is missing, if
property is missing there, instead of
looking into application.properties
which is for all common for all
microservices, it first look into order
service.properties.
Now it got fall back to order
service.properties. It says that okay
uh the configuration is missing into the
Dave itself. Then I will fall back to
whatever the order service.properties
properties has okay because this is
common for QA for all profile Dave prod
this is the default you can say that
okay so first precedence is whatever the
exact profile you are looking for or
exact application you are looking for so
it first look into that
otherwise it will look into the global
one but exact profile so you will see
that the profile is important first so
first preference is always profile
First exact application then the global
one but exact profile if that is missing
here then it will goes to the okay now
for this application whatever the common
for all the profiles I will use that if
it is missing there also then it has no
choice but to fall back to the full
default one like application.properties
properties which is for all
microservices for all profile. Okay.
Now let's say that if that is also
configuration is missing it is not there
then it will fall back to particular
order with each application there is
also application.properties application
div.properties
okay then it will it will fall back to
that local.
So local always has the last precedence.
Okay. So then then it will fall back to
application dave.properties.
If that is missing configuration is
missing there then it will ultimately
fall back to application.properties
local one local means now with your
application whatever the property files
you have application.properties file.
So this is the same thing I have
mentioned here.
Okay.
Now read this term global properties
which I have defined here.
Application.property applies to all
service and all profile. All service all
profile. Application hyphen particular
profile. Application Dave application
hyphen QA application hyphen prod. This
apply to all service but with a specific
profile.
Similarly we have specific service
specific like your application name
dotproperties applies to particular
service. Let's say you have order
service.properties. So this is applied
to order service only particular service
but all profile DF QA prod.
So particular service particular
profile.
Okay. So
this precedence is very very important
where most of the confusion happens.
If you are clear with this precedence, I
think you would be able to properly
clearly understand and manage the g
repository for this config files. Okay.
And also you can just see this this is
the generic of this itself like the
first uh precedence is application name
whatever the particular application you
are trying to search and its particular
profile if that is missing then the
global
but the same profile is the next order
if that config is missing there itself
then the particular application name
dotproperties
okay now this is common like say for QA
dev pro but for particular service only.
If that is missing here then it goes to
ultimate fallback to
application.properties which is a global
for all microser all profiles.
Then after that it fall back to local
a specific microser there application
hyphen Dave or QA whichever you are
looking for that properties and its
local application. is at last. We will
see that with an example. I hope this
step one is clear and the precedence is
very important. Again I'm telling
precedence is very important. This is
where most of the confusion happen.
Now let's move back uh move forward to
the step two.
We have already done the setup of this
config files. Now we have to set up the
config server. So config server is the
one which fetch the config from this
get. So this application which we are
now going to write that ultimately
fetches the property from this g.
So you can open the spring initializer
and from there
we can uh
add this like whatever the version you
want to work with always pick the let's
say uh 1721 whichever you are
comfortable with right and the stable
version. Now here you will see that you
have to pick this
pom uh dependency config server
dependency. Okay. So this brings this
dependency into our pom.xml
spring-cloud
config server. So this is our act as a
server
and its task is to fetch the properties.
Okay. So now let's see that. So first
you have done that you have created this
project and chosen this dependency
config server and make sure that your
pom has this dependency addit.
Now in its application.properties you
have to add certain things.
First thing is you have to provide a g
URI spring cloud config server get URI.
Which g URI? this
where we have provided the
configuration property files property
files right in the g repository so it's
git url we have to provide so this is
the gurl
okay so at this point of time this g is
public so you can directly write like
this you don't need any username you
don't need any password you can directly
give the URI link okay if it is a public
git repo
Okay.
Now the second is configuration is
spring cloud config server get search
path. So here I have created two
folders. If you remember from this I
created two folders here. One is global
another is order service. So I have
provided the search path here.
Search this folders order service and
the global. If you haven't created any
folder and just you have like plain
dotproperty file without any folders
then you don't need this one. But if you
have divided into like proper folders
then you need to divide uh provide all
the folders which it need to look.
Then the third is get.clone.onstart.
So it can be true or false. So if it is
true then what would happen is it will
download the property from central
config at the time of application
startup. If it is false it will be
downloaded at the time of first request.
So now when you going to start this
application config server at the time of
application startup itself it will
download all the properties
okay and cache it.
But if you make it false then when the
first request come not at the time of
application startup when the first
request come at that point of time it
will download it and then put a cache
anyway it will download and put into the
cache but at what time either
application startup or at the first
request that we have to tell. So I would
always say that always use clone on
start during application startup itself
it will download it and put it into the
cache.
And the third uh and the another uh
configuration is get do. Defaulty label
like which from which branch you have to
fetch it. By default is main itself but
let's say you have very u feature
specific changes. So you can give a
branch name from where this property
file has to be fetched. So default is
main. Even if you don't skip this one,
it will fetch it from mainly.
But if you have any different other
branch which is not main then you can
use this get default hyphen label and
you can provide a branch name from
branch name of which this config file
get repository.
Okay.
So this is the thing which you require.
Now the question might have come to you
okay Shan this is the public get repo
link we can directly provide a link and
it would be able to access it. But most
of the cases repos are not public. It is
private. Then what to do? So like this.
So let's say that whatever the uh config
file which I have created this one, this
repo I have specifically made it
private. So you will see the lock sign
here. Now what how to add it? So we need
username and password. And for password
specifically token. So if you're using
GitLab. So in in the gitlab
if you see the right hand side of your
this is your repo and here if you see
three dots within that go to the project
setting inside the project setting you
will see access token
from that access token you just create a
new token and copy it.
But if you are using GitHub,
click on your profile. Within that
profile, go to the setting. From that
setting, goes to developer setting. From
developer setting, you will see personal
access token. Click on fine grain token.
And you can create one token here and
just copy it.
Once you do that in the
application.properties, earlier you have
already provided the URI that is okay.
Still we have to do that. But now we
have to provide this get dot username
get dot password also.
Okay. And it's never recommended to
directly put your username and password
here itself.
Okay. Always put into environment
variable or if you have any server which
manage the keys fetch it from there.
Okay. So for now I am putting into the
environment. So in the intelligj if you
open the run click on run click on addit
configuration there you can add so get
username get username and you put
whatever the username you have so
generally after like whatever the
gitlab.com github.com whatever the name
you have generally that is the username
but you can check your profile uh you
have created into that g account and see
what is the username you have given
generally this is the username so you
you can Put your username like this. Get
username equals to this semicolon. Now
your token get the name I have for the
placeholder is get access token. G
access token. Now paste it your token.
Done. So if you have a private rapper
you have to just add username and token
also. And how you can create the token?
You can see this
um order like this is the way for the
GitLab and GitHub.
Okay. So till now what we have done is
like we have uh created an application
with this dependency config server. We
have added application.properties
provided the get URI what search path
and this what branch we have to fetch
the properties. And one last thing we
have to do is within the application the
main class the main class you have to
just enable the config server at the
rate enable config server. Why it is
required? Because this will turn this
spring boot app into central
configuration server means it will load
the repository file from central config
report during application startup and
expose certain endpoints. So you can say
that if you don't add this the certain
beans will not get initialized.
So when you add this then spring will
get to know that okay you are creating a
config server. Okay, which task is to
fetch the property from the uh you can
say that the central configuration where
you have kept a repository from that it
has to fetch the configuration and then
it expose certain you can say that it
has its own controller where it has
exposed certain endpoint which we can
use. Okay. So this is one of the
endpoint/lication/profile/
label. So let's test till this point.
So I have updated the central config
repo with the property files. So this is
the central config repo which has just
plain property files. Okay, just see
this for global I have added this
application.properties
Dave hyphen prod QA and
application.properties properties I have
put this is the configuration custom dot
message hello from global default so
this is global and this is default like
for all QA prod profiles
similarly for application hyphen dev I
just put hello from global dev since
application.properties properties right
it's a global but hyphen div it's like
global div
similarly for prod you will see that I
have hello from global prod and for qa
hello from global qa
now inside the order service I have this
order hyphen service -
qa and this one so here I have just put
hello from order default the same
configuration custom dot message same
but the message is hello from order
default. So this is the default for this
order service for QA for prod for Dave
but only for order service. So hello
from order default.
So for this one I have just put a
message hello from order Dave. For this
one hello from order hello from order
QA.
So likewise for with one configuration I
have filled this property files
and so my repo is ready and I have
pushed it into the main. Okay. And I
started the configuration server with
the I have done everything and I have
put put this annotation also and started
the application for this configuration.
Now once you start this configuration
and once you have added this annotation
I told you that it act as a config
server it expose certain endpoints
like this
okay
application /profile/ label so now I am
just hitting that one
localhost 8888. So at this this is the
port number which I'm using for config.
So here if you go above
I'm using 8888 for this
config server.
Okay. So this is the config server which
we are creating right. So it is running
on 8888.
So now let's see that.
So first is application.
Application. So I put the application
name order service. What is the profile?
I'm looking for div
and which label main.
So if you don't even provide label right
it will by default look for main. But if
you specifically provide a main then it
will use this like from which
which branch you specifically looking
for. If you don't give it okay if you
don't give it it will look at your
application.properties properties for
config server and if you have defined
there whatever the branch name you are
looking for default hyphen label right
it will use that branch if you haven't
defined that itself it will use main
okay otherwise you can use uh directly
provide into this also now here if you
see what is the order you are expecting
without even looking this what is the
order you are expecting okay just write
down in your copy what is the order so
now here I am hitting order - service
Dave. So it will look for first order -
service - Dave. If configuration is
missing, it will look for application -
Dave. Then it will look for order
service.properties
and last it will look for
application.properties.
So now if you see the response,
it will give me an array. So this array
act as a precedence. So first
first precedence is hello from order
dev. Hello from order dev. So it is
coming from order service
div.tproperties.
The second in the array is hello from
global dev. It is coming from
application div. Then the third in the
order is hello from order default. It is
coming from order service.properties.
And the last in the order is
hello from global default which is
application.properties.
Till this point we haven't added our uh
order application. Okay. So if it is
missing there also then it fall back to
ultimately local. That is the last
that's why the local has the last
precedence.
If configuration is missing here itself
then it fall back to the local.
So till here we have done means our
configuration server is also set up and
endpoint is working fine. If we hit the
endpoint we are getting the response
from the g.
Now the step three is adding the
microservices. So this git repo where
all the properties are present that is
done config server is done which is able
to fetch the file. Now all we have to
write is our individual independent
microservices. Now let's say I'm
creating order microser.
So this is order service. You can create
it. Now remember that this is your
client. This is your config server. Now
this is your config client. So you have
to add this dependency config client
dependency. It will bring this springy
cloudy starter
config. So this is act as your config
client.
Now, okay. So, here if you see on
startup,
this app will contact a config server
during application startup. When you
start an order service at that point of
time, it contact the configuration
server.
The configuration server you know that
it is enabled with this at the rate
enable config server and fetch its
configuration.
it automatically load those properties
into the app environment as if they were
local application.properties.
So for this I I will tell you we will
come with an example for this one. So
we'll this line will commit. So now
let's say that you have downloaded this
created this project you have this
dependency double sure that you have
this dependency added.
Now I have created uh its
application.properties properties also.
So inside this application.property this
one I have provided the name order
service remember that this is the name
only we are using into our centralized
config repo for order service right
order service. So whatever the name you
would give you have to use the same name
in the uh git repository where you are
maintaining the property files.
The second configuration I am adding it
spring.config.imp import
this is the config server
config server
URL okay host and port number you can
use ureka server
okay if you don't want to hardcode it
generally we never hardcode it okay so
you can integrate with ureka server we
have already seen uh how to integrate
with ureka server we have already
covered that so here I have directly
hardcoded the URL but I would highly
recommend that watch out the Ureka
server uh video where we have uh
integrated we dynamically fetching the
host and the port number. Okay.
But before that I have put this optional
config server. What does it mean? I am
telling that hey order service even if
config server is down
you don't have to fail you don't your
application should be able to start up
okay and your source of truth would be
your local application.properties
properties.
Okay. So your source of truth would be
your Dave, your QA, your prod. Okay.
So don't rely. So this is just an
optional. If you if you see that config
server is down or unreachable, your
application startup should not fail.
Okay. But if you skip this
and your config server this one your
config server is not up or down
unreachable your order service will not
even start itself.
Okay. So that's why I have put it
optional.
Then I have put the profile
spring.profiles.active
Dave. Okay. For now I have for testing
purpose I have kept it Dave that hey yes
I am working in the development
environment. So I want to load this Dave
properties
and if you see the profile video also
you can see that there is also a way to
dynamic uh while starting the
application you can provide whether
which profile you want to work. So that
is one way. Another way is that in the
application.properties you can override
like which environment you are working
at. Okay. So both is correct. Now let's
say you are working in the development
environment. You just change that active
profile let's say Dave. Okay. And yes
you have put the configurate custom
message hello from local default.
Similarly for the Dave
this is the message hello from local
Dave and then you have QA hello from
local QA.
So I have defined this property file
also.
Okay.
So now you know the order. Now till this
point you are clear that first this is
the precedence. If the configuration is
missing here in the global default also
then ultimately it fall back to this
local property files. Okay let's say you
are looking for Dave right? So it will
first give precedence to application
Dave. If it is missing then it will goes
to this local application.properties
which is default for Dave qa.
Okay, then you can add the order
controller. Simple in the order
controller you have let's say add the
rate value you are looking for custom
dot message okay and just very simply
using this here into this
and you can try hitting it I am just
hitting this endpoint slash order/fetch
okay this is your order application it
is running on 80080
now if you see that from where it fetch
Fetch order and message. Hello from
order dev. Fetch order and message.
Hello from order dev. So where it might
have come from local. No it has come
from this one. The first one.
Hello from order dev.
Okay.
So then now one question might have come
to your mind. Hey
our order application is running and
someone has updated the central config.
So you have your config
repo here. Now
then you have config server
and then you have order service.
Now your order service is running but
somebody has updated
updated the properties how your order
service will get to know until and
unless you won't do application startup
it will not reflect okay do I need to
restart the app every time anytime any
change happen in this repo
that's where the biggest advantage comes
into the picture it has a you can say
that a feature to dynamic update the
properties.
Okay. So there is a concept called
refresh scope
but for that we have to understand the
actuator.
Actuator.
Okay. So for that we have to understand
the actuator. Okay. So I will cover the
actuator first and after that I will
cover the refresh scope. And with that I
think it would become total clear from
end to end that okay we have
till now created this central
configuration.
Okay. Now all is very important thing
left is dynamic update. Even my order
service is running
how it can fetch the latest changes from
this repo.
Okay, that's where the refresh scopes
comes into the picture. But for that you
need to understand the actuator first.
So see you in the next video and if
there is any doubt feel free to comment
in the uh comment section. We'll discuss
further. Okay guys, bye.